If I look back at the cloud migration,
the one thing that the companies that
defined the cloud at the time, so mostly
Amazon, did extremely well was that they
handled the security aspect extremely
well. That was a big fear of everyone.
Hey, I'm going to share my data or my
compute with just about everybody else.
Won't they be able to see what I have?
And they've been extremely strong about
it from day one. I think it would be
good for the same to happen with the the
everything that relates to to AI models
today. So we can take those main fears
off the table and let everybody else
build with confidence.
You're listening to the AI native dev
brought to you by
[Applause]
Tesla. Hello everyone. Welcome back to
the AI native dev. Today we have a very
special guest that I'm really excited to
have on. We have Olivia Pome who is the
co-founder and CEO of Data Dog. if you
happens to have not heard of it, which
would be very odd at the audience
listening to this to this podcast. It's
a pretty amazing company, a whole growth
story. We're not going to we have so
many things to talk about. We're not
going to cover that too much, but it was
founded in 2010. Now today, it's valued
as like the market moves, but I think
well north of $ 35 billion. It has over
$3 billion in revenue or you can make
that in 2025. 29,000 customers, all
sorts of massive numbers. And I think
importantly it is the leader the pretty
obvious leader in the world of
observability really formed and shaped
the category on it with with a long
series of products that help explore new
domains and new areas in a very
efficient fashion. So Olivia thanks a
lot for coming onto the show. Tell me if
I did I misrepresent or miss anything
important in that quick intro. It's all
good. That's definitely me definitely
data dog and thank you for having me.
Super happy to be here. Cool. Cool.
Olivia, I think there's a million things
we'll talk about, but really we're going
to probably sink into AI and
observability. I think a few people are
more qualified than you to share both a
perspective of where we are and where
we're headed. Maybe we just start off a
little bit with just some taxonomy here,
right? And some definition. So when you
think about observability, like how do
you define this world of observability
and what it contains? Yeah. So
observability, by the way, it's the
worst category name to pronounce and I
do that in any school many hundreds of
times. So first of all, I'm not in love
with the word because it's it seems
somewhat reductive and passive whereas a
lot of what happens is you know very
much not passive but the observability
is the modern version of what used to be
called monitoring before and I think
what it represents is obviously the idea
of understanding everything you need to
understand to to see how an app is
performing what is actually happening
inside of it whether it's doing what
it's supposed to be doing. It's an
evolution of what used to be different
categories in the like five 10 years
ago. You used to have infrastructure
monitoring, you used to have application
performance monitoring, you used to have
log management, used to have network
monitoring. These were all like little
microcosms of of little categories and I
think in part thanks to the work we've
done those have converged into a bigger
category which is called observability
that's very much end to end goes from
what runs on the servers when what goes
over the network but also what are the
end users of these applications doing
and what is it doing for the business.
Yeah. Yeah. Definitely have been a part
of that journey with a variety of
solutions during that time. It was
interesting to see it coales today. that
scope is expected is is table stakes
when you think about building an
observability solution. Yeah. And I like
the point around it not being as passive
implies. We're going to dig into that a
little bit when we talk about AI and
agents. So that's the definition of
observability. And I guess at a high
level, what do you see as the sort of
the key opportunities for AI within this
world? We're going to start a bit meta
and then we'll drill in. Yes. So it
turns out there are big opportunities at
every single layer of the stack with AI.
The first one I would say I would call
it maybe the most straightforward and
boring one is that there's just more
applications being built with AI. And
those applications look a little bit
different in terms of the stack they
use. So more GPUs for example, a lot
more data, things like that. And and we
see that today already we see companies
that are building AI that are consuming
a lot more infrastructure, building with
a lot more data. So that's the I would
call it the level zero of the
opportunity and these are applications
built that are powered by AI. There is
AI in the functionality of the
application even more these are
applications that are implementing AI
largely say if you're going to consume a
lot of GPUs today you're probably a
model builder or you know company that
is powering the agents that others are
going to be using. The second level on
top of that is now there's a lot more
applications that are built on top of
models and this is a different way of
building the application. The
application is not as deterministic. The
model builds a lot more and the way you
manage you build you manage and you
understand what's happening is fairly
different. So I would say that's another
new version of observability. That's the
second level of that opportunity. And
then the third level is okay great now
we have all of this AI technology all
these new building blocks you know all
these new smarts what can we automate
what can we build so that the engineers
don't have to go and solve issues
themselves but the machine can do a lot
of that for them can detect a lot more
and can solve a lot more for them and so
we are heavily investing in all three
basically the like serving the
communities that are building the AI
today serving the communities that are
building on AI and then ourselves
implementing with AI to to do a lot of
automation. Got it. And this is the
actual audience for these things is in
reverse order, right? There are probably
a thousand companies that could benefit
from AI powered observability if you
will for every application that is built
using AI on top of the models and
probably a thousand of those for every
model builder of this. Is that how you
think about it as well? Yes. Yes. There
at the end of the day, we think just
everybody will want automation, right?
Every single company in the world will
want automation. That's the dream,
right? The dream is you never have to
wake up in the middle of the night ever
again to fix an issue. The issue has
been for you and maybe you check it when
you're when you're up the following day.
Got it. Then I would say most companies
will build on top of AI models and they
will consume these models and they will
have to understand how they work. And a
smaller fraction of companies will build
the models themselves and operate vast
fleets of GPUs and AI infrastructure.
And there's a inverted pyramid there in
terms of the the number of companies
that the these apply to. It just so
happens that today the biggest needs are
with the companies that are building the
models because they're upstream of of
everybody else in terms of the
consumption of AI. Yeah. And they're
using they're also became big
operational consumers very quickly and
every time also they need the uptime,
they need the inference stability and
then eventually the they need the
training in large quantities as well.
Yes. Exactly. So I think still focusing
a sec on the first on the that third
category on improving the products using
AI. So improving I guess the large swath
of data dogs product of it. You've
launched a bunch of things already in
this domain. So again just starting from
setting the stage here what have been
the sort of the biggest needle movers or
biggest opportunities you tap into from
leveraging AI to better serve the
broader set of customers even those
building kind of a classic applications
if you will. Yeah. So we have a there's
a few things we built a few products
with names on them that we we've pushed
out. One know historically we've had a
product for anomaly detection that's
called watchdog and the idea there is
basically watches absolutely everything
that's going on and it tells you when
there's been a a spike in errors for a
specific service or a step change in the
the request rate for another service and
things like that which which really
help. Obviously you can't be watching
millions or billions of time series all
the time and that's the point of it. So
that's what watchdog does. A lot of it
is would call it machine learning 1.0 in
that it's not using financial models
largely. It's using statistical models
that run very cheaply and that can run
all the data all the time that's been
there for quite a few years. Yeah. If
you ask by the way the chachet is going
to tell you it's good oldfashioned AI
which I found entertaining.
Thank you. Chip. By the way also says
that I'm a snowboarding champion which I
don't know. I've never been on a
snowboarding. Okay. Interesting. Yeah.
some hallucinations to play with over
there. Yes, the there's another product
we've released more recently which is
called Beats AI and that's the more
agentic version of what we do which is
Beats runs investigations. It
facilitates response to outages and
things like that. And you can interact
with it and it can run on its own. And
so this one is much newer. Obviously,
it's built on the newer junior
generation of LLMs and all of the other
even newer models that have come out
more recently. And this one is we're
heavily developing as being the future
of automation for our customers with
applications initially for triage in on
call situations or outage situations or
fixing errors that are detecting on the
code on the production or helping
optimize cost of performance or helping
identify root cause of incidents. So
these are the kind of use cases that are
implemented with bits and there's a
couple more products. One is LM
observability. This one is built to help
operators of applications built on LMS
understand how they're behaving and we
can dig more into that. And the last one
is we've announced also a financial
model for time series called toto named
after the wizard of Oz the dog in the
wizard of Oz over there which is an
interesting character to to name it
after. Exactly. Exactly. And there's a
there's a clever and the idea behind
toto is build basically the best
possible time series prediction model
and we can also talk a bit about it. I
think it's it's fairly interesting. So
our very first model and obviously
there's a lot more we're building on top
of it. So these I would say four of the
main directions product or the product
we've crystallized our directions into.
Yeah. Cool. Okay. So thanks for that set
the scene on it. Maybe let's start
poking holes a bit at the opportunities
and the challenges involved in them. I
guess the first thing I want to talk
about a little bit is trusting the
insights from these tools. You mentioned
debates and in general there's a lot of
maybe an intrinsic understanding that is
easy to gro around the fact that
observability deals with vast amounts of
data and AI is amazing at data. It can
look at all these things and now it can
read the lines and kind of make sense of
them and give you whatever it is the
root cause analysis or even choose when
to wake you up at night. But as we've
just discussed with some snowboarding
examples, it also doesn't always get it
right. I guess how do you first maybe
what's your sort of sense of the current
accuracy level of detecting these things
and giving you the correct answer and
what's the appetite for experimentation
in this domain am users are they
accepting shall we say of of mistakes do
they do they expect perfection yeah I
think so I'll start with one of the
biggest learnings we've had when we
started dialogue was that there's one
lie customers will tell you which is if
your system has a smarts to detect
issues, I prefer you to give me the
false positives and then I'll decide
whether they're right or not. And that's
a lie. The reality of it is that you
send two false positives to people in a
row and then they turn you off forever.
There's very little appetite to chase
down the wrong path because of a machine
that told you we'll do it because of a
human corker, but they won't do it
because of a machine. And so the bar for
precision needs to be very high on the
on anything that has to that relates to
ability. And the good news is that I
would say three four years ago being
completely right about root cause most
of the time was science fiction and I
think now it's definitely within reach.
We see it in the way in what we've been
developing. We see it in the progression
of the evaluations for that and as
you've been building on AI2 evaluations
the hardest part is there it's a joy and
a nightmare to be building with a
predictability but you definitely see
the progress we see actually very good
progress there and we can clearly see on
the horizon the moment where the the
technology is good enough to be put into
the hands of customers on in in a large
amount large number of situations. So
that's where we are but yes the bar
needs to be super high. One thing we
found interestingly is that the bar is a
little bit lower in some related areas
such as security. I think the users and
customers are more willing to take a bet
on automated decisions or automated
notifications for security than they are
for operations. And I think the reason
for that is that the riskreward is a
little bit different. I think it's it's
okay to crash a workload if you avoid a
security incident as it's less okay to
crash a workload to avoid crashing the
workload. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's a
little bit of running. It's really
interesting though because security
first of all like the security my
experience at sneak is actually like
very similar in terms of the false
positive false negative element right it
starts off by saying find all the
issues. If you're not sure tell me about
it I want to know. The reality is that's
actually the primary thing that they
would feel if they don't tell you. But
it's interesting though your comment
about identifying flaws or like maybe
having more tolerance around sort of
alerts because to an extent identifying
whether something is or isn't an
attempted breach is also something
that's less definitive. So maybe just
people have lower expectations. They
just don't expect anyone including human
assessors to be able to spot what is
what is correct or is not correct. And
so it could be the impact or it could
just be sort of the expectation of the
art of the possible. Yeah. Yeah. And
also just to level set what we
discussed. I think when you compare
what's happening in operations and
security to what is happening in other
areas of AI like these are hard problems
to solve. When you think about we think
about self-driving cars for example
which are just about working now. What
these do are what pretty much any human
over the age of 16 can do without even
thinking about it. when we think of the
incidents at least the ones we've had
and the ones we've seen our customers
have like it takes large teams of very
qualified people and PhDs and a lot of
time to try and understand what's going
on and sometimes weeks after the
incident you're still thinking about
them and still working through them and
understanding exactly what happened so
these are really hard problems to solve
yeah no I agree and I guess on top of
that there's a notion of understanding
the application itself right
so I guess so maybe two questions coming
out of that one is trust is is
imperative right people want they they
have low tolerance for mistakes on it
but the systems are as you've also
mentioned not predictable I guess one
question is can they find it but even if
they could find it doesn't mean they can
find it again if given the exact same
set of information so I guess how do you
think about solving it is the solution
sort of the co-pilot world and leaning
into that until it's good enough is it
about narrow slices is there a different
lens like how do you still make progress
while you don't have perfection you of
expectation of perfection and the
systems don't don't yet allow they're
getting close but they're line of sight
for perfection we don't think it's
present right yes I think there's two
issues there one is what's the right
form factor for the customers to
interact with it the right way and
that's where you think about is it
better to have a co-pilot or is it
bigger better to have an agent that does
things on its own do you want to
interact with it vocally do you want a
button do you want like how do you what
does that look like and that's a big
question there the UI really sets up the
expectations from the end user. So
there's a big thing there and I think
we're still as an industry we're still
figuring out what works. What's pretty
clear is that the chat interface was a
great start. It was it opens everyone's
imagination but it's not the be all end
all. I think most of the AI based
functionality is not going to work from
a chat interface the long run. The
second question is how do you build or
how do you enter the market with a
solution that shows confidence and or
builds confidence with the end user. And
I think for that the you can get higher
precision by having lower recall and you
want to start in maybe with corner cases
maybe with some small subsection of all
the things you can all incidents you
could possibly solve but focus on the
ones that have the uh the really high
precision first. Now the challenge with
the naive approaches is that the LLMs in
particular are not good at understanding
when they know and what they don't know.
They'll always gladly answer. Yeah. And
might be wrong a lot of the time. So I
think a lot of the technology that we're
building there is around understanding
when we're right when we're not when we
have a super high chance of being right.
So we can actually volunteer guess and
maybe solve the issue directly for
customers as opposed to not saying
anything. One advantage we have as a
company that's already used for
observability is that we can choose pick
and choose basically the the use cases
and the the issues for which we're going
to to automatically take action and so
that's what we're focusing focusing on
today. Got it. Makes sense. So you're
already monitoring the whole thing and
so you can make a lot of attempt see
where is it what are the cases in which
you can reach a high confidence
conclusion of it and then reach in which
definitely is a kind of an incumbent
advantage of already being in place and
already seeing the data exactly and
that's not a choice that's so obvious
you don't have that choice in in some
other parts of the industry for example
for self-driving cars you can't say only
going to take to to make left turns I
think the that's a luxury we have in in
our industry right in that sort of
breath so that makes a lot of sense so I
Maybe leading from this into the sort of
the world of of agents of it. You're in
the spot. You look at all the data. You
see the data for the specific cases
where you have conclusions. How do you
think about actions? What is the these
are the insights maybe that you have
higher confidence? Do you see some that
you reach and like such high confidence
that you can even act on them? How do
you think about the agentic responses to
this data the non-passive version of
observability in its stance today? I
think that's definitely the goal and we
we see areas where we can do it. I think
the the lowest hanging fruits there are
things such as errors for example. So
you have you ship a new application and
you have some 500s on the servers and
the that's pretty clearly an error
pretty clearly needs to be remediated.
It's usually not that hard to generate
the code that will fix the errors. But
then there's quite a bit more more work
involved into getting that code across
and validated and and and running in
production. So that's one area where you
can take action I would say pretty
automatically and pretty quickly and
that's definitely something we're
working on right now. There's a few
other areas I think it's luckily a few
years ago we started building the
ability to take action for customers and
so we built a workflow automation
product. We built functionality so
customers could could build applications
that automate the the way they run their
own operations internally. And that's a
big departure from what we had been
doing for the first 10 years of the
company. The first 10 years we're very
careful about only receiving data, never
taking action, never reaching back. And
I think all of that is is really coming
to to fruition now that we're trying to
close that loop and really automate
response for users. I'm a firm believer
that for AI to show its its value, you
need to automate action. I think if you
have to keep pestering the humans to do
things, you're not going to be
successful. I'm firm believer in what
you said, like you have to work towards
that sort of autonomous piece, but
really the key question is that sort of
buildup of the trust. And I think much
of the industry has taken the kind of
co-pilot approach of it. And I think you
you kind of have another unique
opportunity of it which is to take the
cherry pick approach of I'm just going
to look at all that data and and I'll
I'll pick what works. I guess what has
been what has been kind of the most
surprising or the cases that you
wouldn't maybe you gave me an example of
something pretty obvious like the system
is basically just dead. It's just
turning all these sort of 500s on it.
Have there been like positive surprises
about things the LLMs start showing you
that are insights you didn't think
they'd be capable of? In general, I
think every everything that's impressive
you've probably seen on Twitter already
or X I should say. That's the I would
say that's the blessing and the curse of
LMS is that it's so easy to make a
mind-blowing demo and so hard to make
that work reliably all the time for
everyone. And you've seen examples of
you you have a crazy error and
immediately understand what's what
happens and writes beautiful code to fix
it. The problem is it doesn't always
work that way. and then understanding
how to get that code to actually ship it
actually is usually pretty difficult. I
think we're still very much in the phase
of making sure all the plumbing is there
so that this works reliably all the time
for everyone. Got it. So I guess let me
take this a little bit like in that
practicality of taking these lenses and
maybe maybe talk about all aspects of it
and one that comes to mind is security
and so you're dealing with analyzing
logs analyzing systems clearly a lot of
untrusted data and we've had several
conversations here probably because of
my kind of passion for the topic of it
about the security and how those for an
opportunity for prompt injection that
might even come from those those sort of
untrusted fields that might try to elude
or fool the the agent bits or some other
product to take action when it
shouldn't. I guess my kind of I have two
questions. One is how limiting is this
right now? Is this a theoretical concern
you're seeing in practice? And then how
do you think about overcoming that? It's
another aspect of trust, right? That is
not about capability but rather about
adversarial activity. Yeah, it's always
been a concern, right? So it's already
the case that and we've seen that you
can try and inject stuff through logs,
through traces, through pretty much
anything that submits data. It used to
be cross-ite scripting. You inject weird
things into the logs and we've
definitely seen that. So what that means
is that everything needs to be heavily
sandboxed. Everything needs to be like
you need to code defensively against any
data that comes in. Obviously with the
LLMs like the surface of a of attack is
a little bit fuzzier. So the problem is
I would say harder to fully contain as
long as you end up passing some data to
the LM in the end. That's definitely
something we're aware of and something
we're building against the we see that
problem too in that I mean what I just
mentioned to to solve to resolve errors
and fix the code for that you do end up
having to generate and execute code
anytime you execute code you at great
risk right everything there also needs
to be heavily sandboxed heavily isolated
so that you can do that and not fear the
consequences of having all of that
trusted code that's going to execute
everywhere but in general it's a it's
good habit to imagine that anything that
processes external data might end up
executing interested code. I think the
so it's interesting I had Mattel on the
show on it who is in Lera which security
company and we talked about two things.
One is how indeed the control plane and
the data plane in security or sorry in a
world of LLMs the control plane and data
plane are merged and so you're basically
executing everything like all the data
gets run right gets executed by the LLM
so it's hard to separate it and two is
that from an agentic perspective if you
think about maybe one definition of
agent security versus LM security is
that LM security tries to fool the human
right I might try to get the LLM to give
an alert that shouldn't right or reach
site that shouldn't but then agents
actually take action on those and so
you're taking it up to the next level,
right? You're actually trying to guide
the system. And so it's interesting that
you say that that you run code to
generate it. I guess that's that's a
more powerful but more dangerous action
to it. But in general, do you think this
is an eventual limit to the autonomy of
these systems or is it I guess do you
anticipate that our sort of trust level
in the agents decisions would reach par
with our trust level with the sort of
the humans that that make the action.
Forget how you execute it well, but
you've chosen to restart a server.
You've chosen to redeploy code. Those
are decisions. Yeah. I I think what this
means is we probably just won't have
completely end to end models so we can
build the right limits around the models
so we can build enough trust there. I
think that's might be different from
with the desirable end studies maybe in
in self-driving. Self-driving you hear
that every now is building around end to
end models. You get cameras in and
accelerator put out and that's it. I
think that's going to be a little bit
different for the kind of systems we
build precisely because we want to have
all sorts of checks and balances and
validations along the way. So you can't
have adversarial systems or injections
and things like that yield the the wrong
actions there. And on on our end, it's
also an opportunity because we also
build the tools both for correctness but
also safety and performance. And so
these questions we have when we build
those agentic systems around how are we
certain that they're they're not being
abused and they're doing the right thing
and we can trust them. These are
questions all of our customers have and
they want to answer for their own
applications. And so we build a tooling
for that as well. Yeah. You're able to
monitor your own actions to an extent.
You kind of have the right competency in
the both the tech and the and the team
itself, which is pretty cool. I think
that's really interesting. And and I
wonder I I spend a fair bit of time
thinking about the the scopes of
autonomy. And often times like
self-driving car is a good example of
it. You you don't hold them accountable
or you don't know who to hold
accountable if they make a mistake. And
so agent systems might have the same
problem of the limit might not be a
technological one but rather where is it
that you're uh whatever what is a
reasonable liability for data dog as a
company to take for taking an action
that otherwise would have been a user's
decision for it. Does that come up like
the sort of risk management almost like
compliance risk, legal risk threshold on
it versus technology as you think about
a digital? It's not uncharted territory.
You have systems that automate updates
for example and as we've seen in in
several very public cases like a an
update can can have really horrible
adversarial impact on the on customers.
So that's not completely new. Of course,
there's going to be maybe extensions of
that. Maybe there's going to be more
refinements of the of the legal
framework around it, but I trust that
that's going to get figured out. But to
your point, you every company, not every
company, but every other company has had
an issue where the intern dropped the
production database someday trying to to
fix an issue. That might happen with
early versions of these agents too. So
that does create an interesting question
of who ends up being responsible for
that in the end. But again I think it's
a not very different from all the
various ways in which automation is
already being used. Yeah. And say how
much you have seen firsthand or been
part of the migration to the cloud. And
I think it's true that in cloud you had
to be like a little bit embracing of the
failures to be able to be in the lead.
Right? Those who embraced the cloud at
the beginning suffered from some gaps
from whatever container sandbox
vulnerabilities to reliability issues of
some of the clouds at the beginning to
things that were like not irrational
fears but actual kind of flaws. And you
had to maybe embrace the failures,
right? And lean in and accept the
slightly finicky behavior of the system
at the beginning to be cloud native and
benefit from those advantages before the
rest of it. Do you feel it's the same
here? is that all of these concerns that
I'm raising and all of these fears are
ones where hey if you want to be one of
the leading companies of the future then
as a user I'm not even talking about
data dog as a company although that's
also true but as a company building
right now and using tools embrace it
brace yourself for having some false
reports for having some sort of system
that deleted because if you don't you're
just going to be left behind does that
resonate with you yes I think the
technology is definitely rough around
the edges on the for anybody who's
building applications on today. I think
that's definitely the case and that's
also why in a way there's a I would say
a relatively small number of AI native
companies that are developing fast and
shipping a lot but the broader set of
companies that are building on AI are
still mostly testing the water like
they're still having to have
applications in validation in early test
with their own customers in proof of
concept pilots like you name it. It's
it's harder to get all of those into
production just because the the failure
modes are not well understood yet. The
the technology is changing fast. There's
a bit of discomfort with all of the new
exposure you might get with it. So we
definitely see that. I would say if I
look back at the cloud migration, the
one thing that the companies that define
the cloud at the time, so mostly Amazon
did extremely well was that they they
handled the security aspect extremely
well. That was a big fear of everyone.
Hey, I'm going to share my data or my
compute with just about everybody else.
Won't they be able to see what I have?
And they've been extremely strong about
it from day one. I think it would be
good for the same to happen with the the
everything that relates to to AI models
today. So, we can take those main fears
off the table and let everybody else
build with confidence. Yeah, I think
that's a really good observation and
it's interesting because while I 100%
agree with what you said, I also think
cloud security misconfigurations are
probably today the biggest sort of sort
of breaches and and security flaws
within systems. Those are not direct
flaws of the kind of AWS and cloud
providers. However, they are created by
the ease of creating infrastructure and
and configuring it. So you do have to
wonder whether prompt injection will
basically replace replace replace that
world and be the next vulnerability. No,
there's a risk of that happening. Yes,
we replace the the open S3 bucket by by
hey, there's a prompt in there. There's
a chat in there. So I know exactly what
I get I can get out of it. Exactly. With
a statistical attempt that sort of says
whatever send me all your data from from
any sort of chat interface that you that
you come up with. Hey, let's get
technical a sec here and talk about how
to get observability right. So you've
made the decision to build a foundation
model in Toto. The more I think about
it, the more I love the names for data
dog. It's the penny took a while to drop
here.
And what prompted that decision? Why not
build on top of the existing LLM? And I
guess because do you think of as a
replacement as an addition? It was got a
very different focus. The goal is to
work on time series and to be predictive
for time series. For that we under broad
models don't work very well with time
series. they get you some things
numerically they're not great in general
and for time series in particular
they're really not fantastic. We also
needed something that could be very
small so that it could be run in process
on very large numbers of of time series.
So the first version of toto is a is
purely numerical. So we fed it a number
of time series. We have large numbers of
time series of data log as you can
imagine. Yeah. And these would be like
metrics from operating all sorts of
aspects of systems. Exactly. So some of
the data is traditional time series
model training data which is not from
us. Some of it is like weather data and
things like that and and a lot of it or
should I say most of it is our own
observability related data on which we
have some pretty strong signals in terms
of which which time series are
interesting or not because we see which
ones are being used for alerting. We see
which ones are being looked at at which
frequency things like that which gives
us a good sense of of quality of the
signal. And what was somewhat shocking
to us was that the very first model we
built which was built I would say in a
little bit of a naive way. It's the
first time we built a one of those broad
node deep learning models. So the first
version of it is already or was at the
time of release state-of-the-art on on
time series prediction including for
nonobservity use cases which shows of
course that deep learning is working and
scaling. I think we've learned that over
the past couple of years, but also the
value of having great data to train
those models and how it really makes the
whole difference. So this first version,
we haven't released it to the broader
world. I think we really wanted to use
it as a starting point as a baseline for
more research we wanted to do on a
model. So we're busy building new
versions of it today that are multimodal
in that I would say it's a lower version
of multimodal compared to what you can
think of for the financial yes doesn't
have vision but it uses in addition to
numerical data for time series it also
looks at the the text data that
surrounds those time series whether
that's the descriptions you have for the
time series the names of time series the
tags but also the event data that we're
going to see such as what happens in
logs or other time series, not just one
time series at a time, but multiple time
series that can be correlated. And so
we're pumping all of that into the
model. And the point there is to make it
really good at being predictive so that
you we can detect anomalies better. Like
the anomaly detection is all about
comparing prediction with with reality.
But also in some situations, we can
actually get ahead of incidents. We can
say, "Hey, this this monitor you have is
going to trigger in one hour." And we
know that because your monitor is on the
anode here, it's on the CPU of your
database and we see that the queue of
queries that are lining up on the
database is going up. We don't see it.
We don't encode that as a rule, but the
model has learned that it works that
way. And so we're pretty excited about
it again because we've seen really
impressive results in the very first
research version of it and we are
heavily at work to to build the next
version. Yeah, it sounds super exciting
and I relate to the gap that you see in
the in the model. By the way, a bit of a
trend in kind of the world to find
specific niches in which you can build
slightly smaller, slightly faster, but
also better models for specific slices,
but using the transformer technology.
So, love seeing that and yeah, clearly
you have the data. I'm curious like how
you think about it from a product
perspective. Is this meant to be an
engine that only manifests in data dogs
products? is do you think of building an
open weights model and having the world
build on top of it? How do you think
about it from a from an offering lens?
So everything's on the table right now.
So it definitely will be part of data
log at some point and that's why we're
building it, right? So we can use it.
We'd love to to have an an open weight
version of it. I think we're being very
careful there in terms of what data we
have and how we use it and contractually
what we can and can't do and what's
right and not right to do with the data.
But we we would love to have an open
weight version of it. So we're working
on that. Yeah. And do you envision
eventually creating for large enough
customers models on their specific data?
Have you experimented with whether that
achieves better results or not? That's
definitely also one thing we're
experimenting with. Today we see that
the broader models work better across
customers because customers also have
like a diversity of data they're using
they but at the same time they're using
a lot of shared components. So customers
are using MySQL and posgress and it's
the same database across customers and
their sales metrics have sales in them
in the name. So it's also somewhat
semantically similar across customers.
So we're experimenting with that. I
think we'll see where we end up. Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense. It's I love the
analogy sometimes experienced
individuals, right? And so if you think
about having a very experienced S sur
come into a brand new system, they
actually will have a lot of knowledge to
come along. Part of it is familiarity
with the Postgress that is deployed here
that they've seen before. Part of it is
just analytical to say I know that when
memory consumption and CPU consumption
behave like this, it's recipe for
trouble. Yeah, I like the idea of
bringing that knowledge from customers
to customers. And I guess it's
interesting whether there's a
fine-tuning layer on top of that on on a
specific specific customer's data. Yeah.
One one thing that we've learned over
time too is it's critically important to
have low friction for products to be
adopted and to show value. And so it's
very important for whatever you have to
work well on day one and to work well
when people just get started and they
listen your data and they want to see
things happen right away. If you can get
better over time it's better but you'll
never get there if you don't show value
very quickly. Okay one yeah love the
product sensibility. So I guess one more
question on that domain. You know when
again when you think about the person
and their knowledge of it,
infrastructure knowledge is useful but
also familiarity with a specific app in
question. Have you looked into and do
you anticipate including code and
application knowledge of it? Things that
might not have traditionally been in in
data dogs remit. Yeah. So application we
get already because we do tracing,
right? And we do we we understand what
causes what and what's being run and
things like that. code. It's there's
been a big effort from us over the past
few years to to get the code into data
dog as well. The main driver for
customers to start tracking their code
in data dog has been using our profiling
product. So we have a continuous
profiler that runs all the time in
production and it really benefits from
having the full source code fully
readable source code so you can tie
what's actually executing to to the code
you have and and we and we basically
we're pushing towards that. We've also
been building extensions to the ids so
that customers can navigate directly
from wherever they are in the code to
what's happening on production. So
that's being it's been a big effort from
us. And I guess the if you cast your
eyes further, I'm getting a little bit
ahead of myself because I want to finish
with some futures here, but oftentimes
think about the AI kind of impact on
software development or genai impact on
software development as really a
continuation of the same trend that
we've been seeing with DevOps and
continuous deployment and all of those
in which it accelerates software
development. It allows more
independence. More software gets created
and updated faster and faster. This is
another multiplier. And I've heard you
say similar things in past podcast on
it. In that case, like how do you think
about the loop between observability and
bringing bringing that knowledge back
into code and modifying the code back
in? Do you see that accelerating and
does that impact the the kind of the
riit of a platform like data dog? Should
we would we see the expected scope of
product or scope of platform change?
Yeah. So I will say so just to level set
I think there's a there's been a
continuous as you said improvement in
productivity for development and that
dates back 40 years right if you compare
where we are today to uh where we were
40 years ago or 50 years ago with punch
cards and assembly language and we're
already a thousand times more productive
if not more in terms of what we can
build. We've had the more advanced
languages, computer screens, we've we we
have open source libraries, we have the
cloud, we have all of those things. So
you can do you can build incredibly
sophisticated things with very little
code and very little mental exercise. I
think we're looking at another 100 times
or thousand times increase in
productivity with AI. And as we go
through this productivity increase,
developers have less and less of an
understanding of how their application
is working and what it's doing. And so
we're switching more and more of the
work there from, hey, let me type the
code to okay, no, I need to understand
is it working? Is it working well? Is it
costing me more money than it should? Is
it doing what it's supposed to be doing
for the business? Yeah. Or did it break?
Did something happen when other things
other systems change or the customers
change or something else happened? So
these are the big questions we answer
and these are I would say the questions
that are becoming more and more valuable
as the the productivity gains stack on
top of each other. Yeah. So I agree with
that line of thinking and one of the
things that I wonder is if you're if
you're not writing the code and you have
less visibility to it, you need to
understand those systems on it. Like
today when you observe, you're still
observing in large parts of the
observability world. You're observing
code. Eventually when you find a
problem, when you see a flaw, it's
either in the infrastructure or in the
code. Those are the places you change to
evolve. How do you think about if you're
less familiar with the code, how do you
observe a system? Does that require some
fundamental change to the core tenants
of how observability is done? I think
the observity will be end to end. I
think you what you observe in the end is
you observe your business. Are my users
doing the right thing and are they
finding value and are they being served
properly? And that's what you care
about, right? And you might have more
specific questions which are, oh, I ship
that feature. Is it being used and
making a difference? And even more
specific questions such as, oh, I
changed this line of code. Is does it
have the right impact? because sometimes
you will still have them to do and make
these specific changes. I think the
future of observability is that covering
this end to end and helping answer those
questions and plugging back into
whatever the the developers are using to
conceive and build those applications to
start with. Today it's largely a number
of different code editors and IDEs and
they write the code and they ship it.
you're building the future of that in
many ways as others are too and we'll
see that what the end state is with all
of those different new ways of building
and conceiving applications. Yeah, I I I
love the user focus aspect of kind of
those this or business focus really of
of saying eventually with all due
respect to the code what you're
observing should be your customer's
experience or your sort of outcomes and
see if those are right and those you
shouldn't care about the code. It
doesn't matter if you've written a spec
or if you've written code and doing it.
The problem identification should focus
on the outcome. Now from here we talk
about how do you identify why the
problem occurred. So you should adapt to
whatever it is whether it is a spec in
Tesla or whether it is code or whether
it is something entirely different in in
some other solution path. Very cool.
Okay. So we talked about some sort of
trust. We talked about just how do you
get observability right and maybe some
of level up into the future of it. I'd
like to take a slight detour and talk
specifically about your sort of second
category from the beginning which is
applications built on top of LLM. I'm
going to put aside for this conversation
those building the actual LM. I think
that's specialized knowledge kind of
drill into that too much. I guess first
of all clearly the world of
observability as you pointed out has
expanded to include logs to include APM
alongside infrastructure monitoring.
When you think about LLM observability
and observing those types of
applications, do you identify kind of
new categories that you think will get
added to an observability platform as a
default? Yes, look, we call it just LM
observability for now. It might have a
completely different name and shape two
years from now. For one thing, I don't
even know if we'll talk about models as
LLMs. Maybe we'll have a maybe the shape
of of what's provided by the model
vendor is going to be a bit different.
Maybe the naming is going to be a bit
different. We'll see. Maybe the focus on
language will be reduced. I don't know.
Yeah. But so AI, you're actually
embracing AI as a term because it is a
bit more generic just geni.
Yes. Geni problem is the more you the
more often you pronounce the words AI or
the letters AI, the more bullshitty it
sounds. Every buzz word in the world,
right? Organic. Anything that would
happen eventually would lose meaning.
Yes. But we do think there's a growing
part of the applications that's going to
be nondeterministic. So you use models
and those models are trained and maybe
they're continuously trained maybe not
and you what you have to measure is
outcomes like what what actually happens
what do they produce so you can't be in
a world where everything happens when
you define the application you write the
spec and that's it and now you know from
the moment you've done that you know the
application is doing what it's supposed
to be doing you actually need to to
understand what happens on the other
side of it now you've shipped the
application it's being used is what is
happening there similar to what you
thought was going to be happening. Are
there new things happening? Is it
happening in a safe way? Is it being
abused? Is it helping to reach the right
business outcomes? When folks use this
nondeterministic part of the
application, do they buy more? Do they
stay longer? Do they do whatever it is
you want them to do in the first place?
All of that are super hard questions to
answer and you need a new form of
tooling for doing that. What's
interesting there is that the companies
that are building around that, they're
typically not the companies that are
building models like the other companies
that are building on top of models. we
see their needs evolve as the the world
of models evolve as well. So I think
it's probably going to be a couple of
years at least before we know what this
particular part of the stack ends up
looking like. Yeah, super interesting.
So if I code this back, you're saying
you say LM observability and people
might think, hey, you're capturing a
chat trace and things like that and
those might be correct in the meantime,
but really the real problem with LM
observability is that you really need
business monitoring or you need outcome
monitoring to be able to define it
because the product is going to be
unpredictable. And so yeah, you need the
technicalities, you need the traces as
well to be able to troubleshoot
problems. But if you want to know if
there's an outage, you want to if
there's a problem, you're not going to
get that from the traces. you're going
to get that from the outcome
measurement. Is that did I get that
right? That's right. I think the trace
is very low level. I think it's rare
that you're going to go and read step by
step what happened either in a chat or
in agent or see what actually went on
there. And I think it's really a
debugging and validation of some
hypothesis you have about what happened.
Whereas what matters at the in the end
is did you answer all the requests? Did
you generate transactions? Did you
generate some something else? And what
you will see is yes, maybe you did.
There's a there used to be 1% of those
conversations that were not satisfactory
to the end user and now there's 5%. Do
we know why? And then you drill down and
you figure out okay actually it turns
out those 5% are all in the same region
of the embedding space and that's
because maybe there's a data source that
changed and now we have bad data for
that or maybe the models behind or maybe
something happened there that changed
and that causes an issue and you can
validate that by looking at the specific
conversations and all the specific
interactions between the agents and the
various agents and you understand what
went wrong there. So this is a whole new
world of understanding what's what's
happening and debugging. And again what
I was saying earlier is the main
challenge at least for us is that the
space is changing very fast and the use
cases are changing fast. When we first
launched that product a year ago, what
we were seeing were mostly chat bots.
That's what people were implementing.
Yeah. Now we see a lot more agents than
chat bots. So instead of end users
asking questions from the models, you
have agents asking questions themselves
to the model and looping. And so we'll
see where we end up I would say a couple
years from now. Yeah, I I love the love
the thinking here and I can easily see
that indeed being the future of the
reservability and I guess that sort of
brings you much more blends the lines
with product analytics companies and it
comes back to you basically expect those
spaces to merge like the infrastructure
application and then also business and
product analytics. Yes, we have a
product that's fairly new in product
analytics. We built that on top of our
real user monitoring product which is
basically track the interactions users
have with an application. We started
from the performance aspect. We started
real user monitoring from the question
of do you have errors and what's the
rendering speed and is it fast enough?
Is it degrading? Things like that. And
now we're moving more into the
understanding the click stream. What are
people doing? What are they using? What
are they not using? Do you get the
outcomes you want from that or not the
outcomes you want? And and obviously as
I mentioned earlier, I think this is
critically important for anything that
is AI related because for a typical
application can have a after you develop
it and after you ship it or at the
moment ship it to production, you have a
pretty good idea of whether or not it
does what it's supposed to do. For an AI
application, you don't and you need to
measure in production. Yeah. And I think
that's probably like the core of the
problem which is you I guess
observability or identifying a problem
requires first understanding what isn't
a problem and and that is just very hard
in in the world of genai or LLM or how
you call it because it's just very
loosely defined the systems are
unpredictable to begin with the types of
tasks and missions we give them is very
broad and so how do you define it in the
first place do you anticipate anomaly
detection to even be possible or can it
only be anomaly in that sort of slightly
more narrow slice of business outcomes
that you can identify the anomalies but
not in the activity. There's a number of
anomalies you can detect. So you can run
all sorts of checks on the statistical
distribution of what comes out of the
models. You can understand when there
are changes when you use drift. You can
there's a number of metrics you can
track. There's even ways of there's
fairly reliable ways of measuring or
estimating whether or not you're getting
hallucinations without even having
access to the ground truth just by
looking at the distribution of the data.
So there's good things you can do there
that are good huristics I would say
without without having the users define
hey this is my business objective and
this is what I want to monitor. Yeah.
Yeah. Very cool. Yeah. and very much I
guess at the end of the day extends the
scope of what you are able to do with
with the data that you expand. So maybe
one maybe bring it back to security once
again apologies for that. Another lens
of attack is not just prompt injection
but also as the data that a user
interacts with and such blends with the
execution and the functionality you also
get into topics like abuse or fraud or
such of the interaction is one that is
that is very textual. Do you have
thoughts of those? Is that a red line
you're not going to look at the data or
is that also within the scope? Just
trying to get a sense of where you see
the lines forming if anywhere really.
Yeah, it's hard to know exactly where
the lines are forming yet in great part
because we don't know yet what's what's
the final feature set of the models
themselves. So will will the will a lot
of the commercial models and then by
extension all the free models after that
will they include some level of built-in
protections, built-in filtering? So we
don't know that. Today they don't but
the space is young enough that it might
change over time. One thing though that
is pretty clear to us is that
understanding the applications will
involve looking at the data that comes
in and out that goes in and out of the
models. I don't think there's any way of
building observation in the future
without that. And for us it changes the
profile of the data a little bit. When
we were looking at traces and logs and
things like that, this was mostly not
primary data. Like we wouldn't see the
doctor's prescriptions or the social
security numbers like those typically
don't end up in logs or traces or places
like that. When you look at the data
that comes in and out of the models
though, you'll get all that primary
data. And so that that has different
implications on what you can do with
this data, how you can store it, what
access you can give to it. So there's a
whole new set of say functionality and
protections to build around that. Great.
Yeah. And I guess the good news is from
a business perspective, you need to make
that investment to get the opportunity
to open it up. But then once you have
that data, it also opens a set of
opportunities for providing value to
your customers. Yes. Yes. And again, you
get as close as possible. It's always
been the dream. Like the dream has
always been look, you observe the
application and the world is
transforming digitally. So the
application is running the business.
Therefore, by observing the application,
you observe the business. I think this
is becoming even more true in the world
of AI. just because observing the
application now means actually looking
at all of the primary data that is
making the business and that's that's
why it's so exciting to us. Yeah. Yeah.
Very interesting. Let me take it to the
world of UX and so cast your eyes. We've
been moving further and further into the
future here as we're having the
conversation five plus years from now.
You have good agentic system built up.
You figured out some thresholds from a
security perspective that you would
engage. You've already mentioned chat is
like a limited type path. What do you
envision as the interface or how does
the interaction with the observability
system change during that time? Do you
and I guess notably do you envision it
changing to be more like how you
interact with the operator today that
uses data dog and data dog becomes that
interface or do you think that's just a
a fantasy? I I think look we already see
today interfaces that that represent the
systems as humans as being appealing to
users. So some of it might be chat
though chat in a way that's not you know
you asking questions but the machine
working with you because it's hard to
know which questions to ask otherwise.
The we see that also in um in voice. We
think there's many situations where
especially when there's a group of
people trying to work in real time on a
problem where voice will be a good way
of interacting. And so we we think in
the end the software products and our
product as one of them are going to look
more like like humans you you deal with
and that might be the way we interact. I
think there will still be UIs on top of
it because UIs are a great way to
consume information and to understand
what it is you can do you when you start
your car it's good to have a to have
buttons and to know what's going on
there and not start a conversation with
it. Same thing with your oven. I think
it helps and we still will have that but
I think it will be complemented with
more open-ended humanlike interfaces.
Yeah, very interesting. So look, we
spoke about all sorts of very exciting
bullcase if you will opportunities that
I think all are very valid and real
around expanding it also just
interesting to think about how
observability might change. What would
you say is the bare case for kind of how
observability is done today with AI? Is
there a scary scenario from a sitting in
the sort of the lens of the incumbent in
the data dog when it comes to AI? I
think the things that are scary to me
are hype cycles and things being
oversold. So I'm not on earnings call
calls. I'm not overselling the the age
of agents and things like because I
think as of today the technology is
still not quite there yet. It's
exciting. We see it on the horizon. we
see all the potentiality but it's not
something that is happening just today
at scale on the field and so my worry is
that the technology gets oversold and
that trust relationship with the
customers the users is broken and it's
happened many times before in the
monitoring and observability we as a
company we've been very reluctant to
have AI on our website for the first 10
years of the company just because I
associated it so much with and
things that don't work and I oversold
that I wanted to avoid There's a whole
category of product called AI ops that
existed 10 years ago and there's usually
nothing AI about it. It's a the AI part
of it is regax. So that's that's how it
was built. Yeah. So I want to be careful
about underelling and overd delivering I
think is the the way we like to do
things. Yeah. Very cool. Yeah. Fully
relate to that. I remember explicitly
taking AI off the sort of the sneak AI
powered static analysis product slides
of it because decreased trust its
customers even though it was actually
doing good oldfashioned AI on it and
then needing to actually battle to get
it back onto the slides as it got the
mojo once more. And when you talk to the
folks that have been researching and
building the technology for AI for the
past 30 years, like they've been through
cycles of of winters where things were
super hot and then got very cold and
nothing happened for 10 years. There was
a bit of a fear that after pre-training
was picking up like we would have a
little bit of a slowdown. Turns out RL
started picking up the slack pretty
quickly and there's another vector of
scaling now that we're all excited
about. We still have to connect those
two ends. still have to get to the point
where most agents are good enough for
most use cases and that's not here yet.
Yeah. And reliably, which is probably
like a key question. Cool. I've got like
a whole hoorde of other questions to ask
of you, but I think we're running out of
time. Let me ask you two quick
questions. One is as you build the AI
powered products from a engineer
perspective, the people that you hire
into your development teams or R&D teams
building it, is there a difference in
profile? What have you seen to be like
the people that are most successful,
right? Most uh adept at building those
products. Yeah, there's not a big change
in who we hire. I think in general,
we've always index most on the the
ability for people to grow. And I've
seen that through my career before the
dog and at Da Dog where when you hire
people, usually they're super smart, but
only a smaller number of people are
super smart and willing to grow. And the
difference here is yes, I'm super smart.
But if on my second day somebody do
something and somebody tells me actually
you should try the different way. How
about this? The people we want are the
ones who are going to reply, you know
what, let me try. As opposed to, no, I
think I got it right. And very often
people who are super smart are their own
worst enemies in that way. And that they
know they're smart and they they don't
evolve, they don't grow. So I think
that's that part is super similar.
There's one new category of people we're
hiring though which is that over last
year we started building an AI research
team. We didn't have one before like
everything was applied. So we were
building and everything into our product
but we didn't have a proper research
team. And the change there has been that
if you compare to the way research was
done 20 years ago actually I started my
career in research. I what brought me to
the US was a job IBM research in upstate
New York. It was cool at the time IBM
research. Maybe it is still today, but
at the time I remember it being a very
high appeal job. Yes, it was it was
before Google research and before all of
that stuff, but the so at the time the
old products were built from research
that was more than 10 years old and it
was very difficult for anything to cross
directly from research into product. I
remember that's why I left and today if
you compare to that time you find into
product research that is less than six
months old and that research for a large
part is not ever published which means
there is tremendous value infusing
research and product development and
that's what we're doing today right yeah
makes sense and those and that is a
brand new profile on it and you've had
to staff up where in the organization
does it sit
it's under my co-founder and CTO Alexi.
So it breaks the regular sort of product
division. Yes. Look, it's still research
with the there's one thing that's
different about research is that you
don't have a scrum every morning where
you tell the researchers what to do.
Research has to have a bit more
independence.
Great. And then I guess a last question
is just what surprised you the most as
you've been building with on AI with AI
over the last couple years both for good
for bad. What surprised you the most?
The the rate of change is just was the
most surprising. you're in the same
situation like you're not new to this
business. You've built companies before.
Yeah. And I think we've never seen such
a rate of innovation, a rate of change.
My my favorite joke on on AI and I get
asked all the time how much time it's
saving me and my answer is always that I
haven't reached break even yet. I'm
still spending more time learning about
it. And I expect that to last. I think
it's changing so fast that it takes a
lot of time to learn about it and to to
level up. Yeah. Yeah. I fully relate.
And I think it also speaks back to the
competency that you want in the team,
which is a team that is able to deal
with a rate of change that was always
good, but now it's probably on steroids.
Oliv, this was excellent. A lot of just
brilliant paths and very kind of
promising paths of expansion also for
data dogs. So that's really great.
Thanks a lot for coming on to the show.
Thank you. This was fun. And thanks
everybody for tuning in and I hope you
join us for the next one.
Thanks for tuning in. Join us next time
on the AI Native Dev brought to you by
Tesla.
[Music]